[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
hello everyone and welcome to the store
the stowa is a digital campfire where we
gather to coherent dialogue
at the nice edge of what matters most
and what matters more than the conflict
between the sexes
so today we have the philosopher queens
myself
and rachel haywire and we're going to be
talking about
a new series that we are beginning with
this initial
chat between the two of us to frame a
set of metaphysical questions
uh questions about the female human
condition questions about
uh who are we becoming what are the
kinds of role models that we have out
there
and what is this new path the path of
the philosopher queen
so the format of this event is going to
be like many of the other stone events
we're going to do about half an hour of
banter between the two of us where we
contextualize this project
and talk about our own experiences kind
of coming into our
senses of the of the female condition
and then we're going to turn
to questions from the audience and we're
going to do something special
where for the first initial wave of
questions we're going to ask
the women in the room to come forth with
their questions for us
so we're very excited uh to start this
project i think it's going to be really
interesting
and what's that rachel
tell me what inspired you to
create this this idea of the philosopher
queen
series here at the stoa hi
raven and hi everybody thank you for
coming
i was inspired to write the philosopher
queen manifesto initially
because i noticed there was a new
current or perhaps
an old current that was resurfacing
of a divine feminine nature
that was very powerful
a bit dark according to some yet
in need of exploration
and i wanted to
bring forth this archetype or resurface
this archetype so we could discuss what
was happening
and i dubbed us the philosopher queens
were
not tradwives um but we're also not
social justice
activists we're femme fatales we
occupy an interesting space and
i believe it's time for us to explore
this space
great i'm gonna just read um a little
bit of the philosopher queen manifesto
uh just to contextualize what we're
talking about here i've threw the link
in the chat so if you'd like to
to look at um the medium post that kind
of outlines
rachel's thinking it's right there so
i love that you begin with camille
paulia so i'll be right up front about
my
influences here i'm currently reading uh
sexual personae
uh which is the magnum opus of the
heretical feminist camille paglia
and um i would have to admit that a lot
of my views as a feminist
um come from her and she is a very
controversial figure within the world of
feminism and i think that
that's kind of partially what uh rachel
and i
are drawing from which is her lineage
um her lineage which is very primarily
interested in
the great mother and these like dark
qualities of the feminine that are often
kind of pasted over with these ideas
that have um kind of persisted of a
purity
or kind of the virginal aspect of the
feminine
so the beginning of the philosopher
queen manifesto
begins with the greatest philosopher
queen herself
camille paglia once said that there is
no female mozart
because there is no female jack the
ripper i posit that by the same token
there is no male sylvia plath because
there is no male courtney love
gender comes in cycles and that which we
do not reveal
becomes that which the world desires
along this line of reasoning there is no
female equivalent to the hell's angels
and if we join a gang like the hell's
angels as an obscure
gesture of folklore this is quite
different from an intellectual pursuit
we are out in the wild attempting to
investigate to domesticate ourselves
into the feminized society we feel too
masculine for
yet we yet are we really that masculine
or are we simply not the plastic healing
goddesses we are supposed to be
on instagram categories such as hashtag
boss girl and social justice activist do
not define us
and never could contain us we were not
second wave feminists and we were not
third wave feminists
we were something in the middle yet
unable to connect with these waves that
crashed the oceans of our desires
this is fine and this is natural and
this is what is going on here
it is time for us to come forward and
define ourselves once again
as our previously obscured current is
beginning to take
shape let us reveal only half of that
which we know
and admit that even half of that is too
much
we are the philosopher queens or pardon
me we are
philosopher queens we are the rising of
the divine feminine
in its phonic form we are philosopher
clean queens
we blast open the doors of perception
and explore the deepest areas of our
minds and spirits
we revive the power of chaos in her
original essence as our new order begins
to take
we are philosopher queens we are the
origin of every story
i think you really encapsulate the
dionysian here um
rachel so there's some like metaphysical
terms that
we've already kind of began to use which
i think would be worth
discussing um we
talked about the you have the sonic in
your in your manifesto
can you tell me a little bit about what
the sonic means to you
yes it's the deep it's the obscured
it's the hidden the forbidden the taboo
the transgressive it's
that which is kind of lost over
by i guess you could call them the
healing goddesses the
the chakra police if i did some
names for them um but um a lot of the
origin is
in the root of cthulhu you know like um
camille talks about
the forbidden zone i don't know if you
guys saw the
film the forbidden zone but it touched
on similar themes and
there was a dark goddess philosopher
queen
who was one of the main characters in
the film
the forbidden zone and it talks about
this mystical force of the this chaotic
power
yeah so the so the phonic you know is
like the bowels of the earth right and
so
in the metaphysics that camille charts
out in her book sexual personae you have
the
ability which is associated with reason
and delight and order and purity
kind of exemplified in the art of greek
culture for example
the kind of beautiful beautiful boy
posed
in a kind of contemplative way with
these
sharp delineated edges right these are
the kinds of textures of the apollonian
it's also associated with masculinity
and the dionysian
is that which the apollonian is actually
attempting to run away from
the dionysian has the qualities of
murkiness
there's like it's muddy it's it's got
all of this
um like disgusting
kind of qualities to it and but it's
also the place where
we celebrate and we we go into kind of
hysterical frenzy we go into
um religious experiences and
have these kind of mind-altering moments
of singularity and the phonic is an
element of the dionysian
and is that which is the most kind of um
renegaded to to the bowels of the earth
that which is hidden
and so there's an element of this that
for me
just on a personal level it's kind of
like why would these abstractions be
helpful
like why is it helpful to think of the
apollonian as masculine or the or the
dionysian is feminine and
i've had lots of conversations with
friends of mine who kind of push back on
this idea that there is any
necessity in like making these male or
female
qualities but for me it's actually been
extremely helpful to kind of come to
terms with the dark feminine in my own
experience
and to admit to that which is
uh dark and powerful there's also a
sense of which the
the female as a victim as some sort of
kind of
pure force that is uh
passive and things come to her
and in that metaphysics you know she's
not necessarily responsible for that
which she does
and the element of the dark mother
the great mother is that of the
devouring mother
the mother who eats her own children
you know who has a kind of power that's
charged by the bowels of the earth
and this is seen in at least in paulia
as
nature you know the apollonian is the
force that turns away from nature
and so we have this kind of tension or
this conflict between the circular the
recurrence
that which repeats itself from one
generation to the next
that which is the mother to the daughter
who becomes the mother
who then gives birth to the daughter and
as that continues on and on
um and then you have the apollonian
which attempts to differentiate itself
and that is difference
so you can also see it within a delusion
sense which is
difference in repetition which is one of
his most influential books
um the dionysian is the repetition
and the difference is the apollonian um
and this is all metaphysics and
you're here for philosopher queens um so
um pardon if if the if the philosophy is
kind of a lot to take in but
uh both rachel and i are you know
drenched
in in metaphysics and in philosophy
and um that's part of my interest here
and and for both of us too we want to
bring in
women who are specifically philosophers
who are working through these ideas who
are
confronting some of these dark elements
that i think um
both of us maybe share different kinds
of critiques of feminism but certainly
this idea of like the pure goddess
um who's like kind of this perfect form
who has no
evil to her i think is a reduction of
femininity
and rachel i think that you share that
view as well
um yeah i really do because
people think about the disney princess
and then they think about the
disney villain you have ariel on one
spectrum and then you have ursula
on the other end of the spectrum but in
the manifesto we say well what if ursula
was hot yeah you know what what if there
was a synthesis
you know but what if the the celebration
of life this this chaos this nature
it was about the roots the origin
the mother the giving birth to uh new
current and what if this
was metaphysically a phoenix rising
through the ashes what if it wasn't
something to shun you know um what if
this was a very
powerful force that we were only just
now
beginning to truly reckon with and you
know through the ages we've
had everybody from joan of arc to
amelia earhart to philosophers like
cathy yacker contemporary commenters
like you know power um even visual
artists
like joan coke who embody the death
and the rebirth and the cycle of nature
and
my question is what are we going to do
with this energy what what can we
as philosophy queens
happening with this current and what are
we exploring
and i was having a conversation with
raven earlier where she was telling me
about this trip that she had and i i
would love
for you raven to get into this because
it just sounded
really groundbreaking from what you were
telling me
yeah thanks for the question rachel um
so yeah this weekend i went on a camping
trip
and took two doses of acid and ended up
having a very archetypal experience
um and it i don't know
i think that there's a variety of kind
of experiences that people have on acid
but i have a tendency to kind of
um you know time begins to
[Music]
phase in from multiple aspects of my
life and so i was
i was kind of walking through a time
that was both my time as a child as a
little girl
and also my like experience of my mother
um who for me there's a kind of special
relationship that i have with my mother
because she passed away when i was 19.
and so there's always this this attempt
to reconnect
or to empathize with her with her as a
figure
um because i have this absence of this
mother figure in my life
and so i i had this moment where i was
climbing up these these boulders up to
the top of a mountain
and the sun was pouring down upon me and
there was a moment of which i was
looking at my body and i look like my
mother
i have her body and i have her face and
i have her being and i was looking at my
hands
and i had this singularity where i
felt that i was my mother and i was also
myself
and i was also a sister and i was also a
daughter and i was also a lover and it
was all happening in a single moment
and i like broke down behind the
boulders and started kind of
sobbing in this uh hysteria of of this
moment
and for the rest of the trip i i was
like in i was
occupying this the space
of multiple modalities
and to me this was like peak dionysian
right it was like it was an embodiment
of this like property of of like female
existence which alexander bard talks
about
um which is the mother and the daughter
are not different
you know they don't need to be different
if anything there's actually a danger in
their difference
that they may not pass down that which
has been learned
from the female line and so there's a
kind of sameness
that exists within femininity um
and then that to be kind of embodied in
my experience and how i was relating to
all the people around me
you know as as this mother figure i was
reading out loud
and you know i had a friend put her head
on my chest
and i was thinking about how as a child
i put my head
on my mother's chest and heard the
vibrations
of her body as she read to me and i
thought about myself
teaching my own child how to read and
then i thought about all the women
who've taught their children how to read
you know so there's this kind of there
was this ricocheting of empathy that was
rooted in all of these different aspects
of the feminine experience that was
happening kind of in the singular
moments
um that i was going along with with all
of these trips
and some of the i mean i'm still kind of
processing
um in the wake of this experience and of
course
there were also other kinds of um
little tiny dramas that happened um that
would we could blow up and maybe do
analysis of but i think you know i think
that this is sufficient
um to kind of talk about this point
which is that
inside of the feminine experience is
these multiple dimensions and it's
you know the the try the triad of the of
the feminine the maiden and the mother
and the crone you know is a pretty
um ubiquitous understanding of
femaleness and
i think that this really uh at least in
this moment really resonated with me
in the sense that i could feel myself
being all of these things simultaneously
and so there's a kind of strangeness
because there's also
and i think rachel you can totally
identify with this as well there's
aspects of myself that are
i consider to be very masculine so
there's
there's like an attempt to synthesize to
exist with and
really embody this this you know
um the singularity of the female
experience and to put it front and
center you know for me i i like heavily
identify with motherhood
it is the most important thing
that i think i can do in my life is to
like have a child and
that's not something that everybody
believes of my generation and i'm not
prescribing it for anybody else but for
me that is like a central value
and it pushes me forward into adulthood
it makes me look at the things about
myself that i need
in order to grow in order to take on the
responsibility for someone else and for
someone else's life
and it also has me empathize with my own
mother who
i basically can only access through
these these
thought experiments um because of her
absence in my existence
but at the same time there's all of this
possibility
of being a woman now that hadn't been
available to women before
that you can walk in the world of men
and also be a mother
you know whereas in the in the history
it would have been if you were to walk
in the world of men you were a
prostitute
there weren't really these types of
fluid roles
um and so there's a sense of which i'm
grappling with this
synthesis of these qualities the desire
to take on
you know deeply this like role of the
feminine that is like an inherited fact
of like
being of this female lineage but also to
engage in the opportunity
of the masculinization of society and
the democratization of opportunity
that we now have as as women
yeah i i would echo that sentiment and
i've developed a deep respect for
motherhood as someone who can bring a
background where people were
kind of like against you know on the
traditional family you know hanging out
in a lot of more like
goth subcultures um which embodied
the dark goddess which embodied the
mother figure
but at the same time that they were very
against having kids so i'm kind of like
having
come full circle and having talked to
a lot more mothers and women who want to
be mothers i'm beginning to see
how it all connects and how it is all a
part of the same lineage even if you
think about the
different archetypes like kalimata
goddess of chaos
the goddess of destruction um but the
question is like what happened after
the destruction or rebirth um aphrodite
we have all of these different
archetypes
of women and the question is
do we embody all of them how
do we understand our lineage
as women from different parts of the
world
with different backgrounds with with
different ideas
um and operating in the world of the
masculine is is definitely something
that i'm familiar with having
been involved in a lot of male
industries and
everything from technology to politics
um
and i did notice that there was a lack
of a female presence in a lot of these
worlds um
because women didn't want to be
perceived
as masculine um which
i think is kind of reductionist because
it is possible to embody masculine
traits and be a
divine philosopher queen you know i'm to
turn it back to the
philosopher queen theme um that that is
okay we can
embody the masculinity and not breathe
in this world of men while
still being a part of this lineage of
powerful divinity and i don't think that
there's necessarily
a contradiction in that and i know there
are a lot of women who feel
you know i'm well i'm not trapped enough
you know i'm not feminine enough i'm not
masculine enough
but what is like like you are you
you are a woman you have that internal
power
you are a part of this lineage and
you should simply be
yeah i mean i think
i think i i both i completely understand
what you're saying like there's no need
to like to see oneself as in lack
right like to see oneself is needing to
kind of either be more feminine or more
masculine to kind of
fabricate oneself based on a sense
of what one ought to be right like i
think that there is
absolutely a kind of fallacy in that but
there's also
there is some kind of strangeness and of
course people debate this and
paulia has a famous quote one of her
most controversial that is
you know if civilization had been left
up to women we'd all be living in
grass huts um and i i mean i love it i
love that
like i i guess for me it's um the idea
that
philosophy is a male pursuit or civil
the building of civilization has been a
male pursuit that it has been
actually um an an act of terraforming
that comes of the male
um impulse to turn away
from the feminine to turn away from
nature
um i don't find anything wrong with that
and
i think that's that's a very paulian
thing i mean she
she is like interested in the riches of
culture which are often attributed to
men
and so there's a way in which this this
like amazonian feminism that she
uh she prophetizes is not afraid
of the existence of masculinity or the
riches of masculinity that which has
brought
great culture and and great literature
and great philosophy
and political theory into the world
and i follow in that in the line of that
but what follows also from that is a
kind of understanding that the
femaleness that i am
is not that which is exclusively created
by femininity
but has been also what men
have created the
stories men have told about women and
how sexual personae have actually been
produced through the likes of
shakespeare right like shakespeare
wrote these characters of femininity
that really um
you know someone like rosalind from as
you like it or cleopatra from anthony
and cleopatra
these characters that were so rich and
full of emotion
um that actually occupied roles that
women in society of that day
would have not had the opportunity to do
um
and that sits in the consciousness it
makes an imprintation on reality
um and it carves out the possibility of
an alternative way
for for women and i think that you can
chart this throughout
um the western lineage where like the i
the notions of being female have
actually been notions
that men have written in many cases and
it wasn't until
um you know a couple hundred years ago
that we that women were given the
opportunity to write about their own
experiences um
and in that sense they were also doing
something that was considered to be a
male pursuit
so there's so much complexity in the
situation
in terms of the dynamics between male
and female and the preservation of the
polarity i think allows
for the tension to kind of persist
and of course there's also these these
people in between and
actually that is who the artists have
been um you know the male artists
who who predate who produce great works
of literature
often were kind of androgen and same
with i think rachel and i we we
actually occupy the space of the
androgen um
and in that space you move between roles
you actually explore the possibility of
being that which is
not poll polarized um
but you still don't i mean i think that
the difference between
maybe the metaphysics of of
paulia or some of these other folks is
that there's a there's a desire i think
in contemporary thought especially the
pop cultural kind
to devour the polarity we we want to
cannibalize it we want it to basically
be
made completely horizontal um
so that the mixing all that exists is
the dyneesian at this point you know
just like the bottom
of of things kind of the flatness of
things the
delusion plateau let's say um but i
think
you know in acceptance with the idea of
the apollonian is like no the polarities
are actually
not only are they uh you know functional
they're just
real you know there's a sense in which
these polarities exist
um as as categories transcendental
categories that have
um real kind of attributes
in reality and when we don't look at
them they come for us i mean that's
actually part of the thing it's like if
you don't look
and you don't consider the great mother
and her devouring nature
she'll come for you she'll come for you
and she'll eat you
right so it's like and i think that that
you can see that in your manifesto right
you talk about the half that is revealed
that half that is concealed
the hat that is concealed if you don't
account for that if you don't see
that like this is the person who reveals
yourself only half
and a half you don't account for that
that which you cannot see
it eventually it will come for you
because you've reduced the person
to only this kind of pure pure element
maybe the trad element or whatever and
you don't actually see
this this sonic element that
is actually kind of where the power lies
that's exactly where the power lies i
think of a show true blood
where there was this character mary ann
she was a main ad
um i think that's the proper
pronunciation where she
devoured everything that was in her path
and it turned out that she was acting on
this very
natural primal impulse
talking about this primal instinctive
nature
that a lot of the characters in true
blood weren't able to
grapple with um and you know of course
they they villainized her
um but if you really think about it
these are the women who have
changed history these are the women i'm
in between the
female the androgen as soon as alexander
would call it the end androgyny
or something and georgia i can't
pronounce it um but yeah he has the word
for this um where it's people who
operate
and between the male and the female
girls and
i think that's very crucial because
we're we're so
polarized with gender right now um
and i i think there's like this desire
for i guess you could call it on like
frivolity
or insincerity that a lot of women are
adapting you know where everything has
to be
like some un serious you know me
and more or joke um and then there's the
other side
which is like the the hashtag self-care
activists
and it's important that we look at
other opportunities um other forms
and other archetypes and understand the
the history of this current um
where it came from where it is now and
where he's going i think back to the
xena the princess warrior and
how incredible xena the princess warrior
was um
and then wonder woman came out like 15
years later
and i'm like well this is kind of boring
why do we need wonder woman
when we have xena you know i mean that
seemed to me like
like a regression i'm not meant to get
off into a
a pop culture tangent um that where
are the bad amazon chicks right um so
there's a lot to be explored
in this realm and i encourage everybody
here
to explore it and to
understand it yeah absolutely
yeah i think we can kind of see um i
mean even here at the stella right
there's like a pretty
there's a strong observation i mean it's
just an observation i
i wouldn't go so far to say it's a
critique but there's an observation that
there's a pretty heavily
heavy skew um towards men rather than
women
and so this is the you're right i'm
racking my brains like why is this the
case
right and i think like the initial like
for me i
i am not really interested in
accusations of misogyny or sexism
um that is not the first thing that i'm
going to look at i think that that is
like
a um knee-jerk reaction and it doesn't
it
if it if there is a case of misogyny or
sexism which i have personally not
experienced here at all
um to to make that be your kind of
declaration of the problem
i think is also to obscure maybe some of
the underlying dynamics that kind of
create
excuse to begin with and of course this
you know this um series is an attempt to
try
and attract this conversation
attract other women and i think part of
it is like
we're so distributed and all these other
groups you know
and uh there are just fewer women who
are interested
in in philosophy let's say and so we
have to kind of get them to congregate
and
i'm hoping that this can be kind of part
of that right because
we we want to be together
um i feel such a longing for female
relationship and i mean that's part of
why rachel it's just been such a gift
to get to know you over the course of of
this year and to work with you
and to have someone in my life that i
can share this type of
uh very you know abstract kind of niche
you know interest and like you know
duluz and alexander bard and like all of
these like weird things that pretty much
you know nobody else really knows about
um to have someone like you
is uh it's like it's like a sister a
sister in the darkness
um to move through this this territory
that
um otherwise feels pretty
uh isolating and i hope that we can
you know draw more uh women who are
interested in these things
and yeah that's
that's so touching to me thank you so
much
my heart right now um yeah i feel the
same way and
i i feel like there are a lot of other
women out there like us who would love
to be
a part of the philosopher
queen series of pastela um all of you
here
if you know of any women that you think
would be interested
we want to bring them on board we want
to stop we want to talk to them we
speak about their interests we want to
host panels with them
and um you know we just we want to bring
more women on this wavelength
into this community because we think
that
it's a beautiful thing and i think um
with that maybe we should start taking
questions or
yeah so um women in the room do you have
any questions if you want to you can
just raise your hand
and uh if you please feel free to ask us
any question
and challenge us on our on our
underlying axioms as well
i mean i think that this is um it was
really important to
yeah like challenge one another and try
and
you know okay um
yeah and if you if anyone else has
questions you can go ahead and put them
in the chat
and let us know what you're all
thinking before i start calling on
people
hi lisa hi thank you what are you
thinking
i'm i went in several different
directions at the same time i just want
to first thank you
both for when i saw this i instantly
thought well this is so cool because
it's
first of all i know it's not an
accusation of
misogyny and yet we're having the
conversation
so i love the both and of your starting
position
um so many things popped to mind the
first thing i
did was i grabbed my iching
because uh what your conversation about
alexander bard and temporality and er
temporalities uh especially intrigued me
i'd love to hear you
go back and forth a little bit about
that but
um what came up for me was the
48th hexagram the well
and uh the the inexhaustible
and i think that really relates to like
donald donna haraway's work
and the sonic and various other themes
that you've touched on
so that that chaotic that depth
that inexhaustibility that temporality
um that's what is sparking in me right
now i don't know if that was a question
but i'd love to just hear your thoughts
sure rachel do you have any thoughts
about
donna harway or the or oh yeah
oh my god so donna herrera was one of my
big inspirations
when i became a trans humanist i read
the cyborg manifesto
and she was one of the first women to
really go against identity politics and
she
didn't talk about misogyny she didn't
talk about victimhood she talked about
how women were kind of stuck in
these human forms when we could be so
much more than that
and i i see donna harvey as a big
inspiration for
so much of the philosophy and so much of
this dialogue and
thank you for mentioning her
yeah definitely i think it's interesting
donna hairway so and i think that this
is maybe a kind of conversation we have
i know that you're no longer
like really affiliated with
transhumanism but um there's a there's a
thing about transhumanism that
um you know the xeno feminists say
nature is unjust change nature right and
so that kind of leads us to
a conclusion of the alterations of our
bodies to kind of transcend
the qualities of the feminine condition
um
the way that i would differentiate this
is that there's a female experience
but there's also a female condition and
that that is rooted in the biology of
the body
and i think the female experience is
something that can be
decoupled from the female body and to me
that it kind of explains
transness as as a meaningful
element of femininity but also the
condition of the female body
um as a as a womb you know as
this entity that
human life incubates inside of
um i think is something that
donna and the xeno feminists rightfully
identify as tyrannical
it's a tyrannical force it is a
condition it is something
that you have to endure and in that
sense i think that
uh you can go two different ways with
this you know you can
you can liberate yourself from that and
that's like the kind of transhumanist
roots that's his you know feminist root
that is like let us transform our bodies
so that we may transcend
this condition or um i mean for me
i've taken the root of embracing this
quality of my existence
and um that's where the kind of mother
archetype comes in
i take this incubator
as my own um and you know
that is like part of how i'm developing
my um
understanding of the female condition as
i move forward in my life and i think
that
uh it's an interesting thing the
condition of birth
and of incubation
as a feminine as a female experience you
know
is at the very least a
necessary kind of empathy for the
condition of femininity
as it has been in the past um now
of course we've had a decoupling of sex
from reproduction
and so we're kind of living in the wake
of this new era um where
sex is is not that which it has been
before it doesn't have the same kinds of
risks it doesn't have the same kinds of
uh
like qualities to consequences to it and
so
this um i don't know this kind of
decoupling and the splitting and the
technological intervention um
that allows for women to transcend their
bodies i think is you know it's totally
unprecedented and it creates these new
you know the cyborg manifesto it creates
the possibility of this um
world of synthesizing with machines um
that can
for some women provide them an exit from
the female condition
um which some women are interested in uh
i personally am not i think i can go in
a lot of directions um
and i see other kim singer recovering
um yeah so transgenderism these days
it's just about immortality
and i think there's so many more
possibilities than
immortality um i i would consider the
xeno-feminists to be post-humanist um
even even future oh yeah that's true
yeah because
transitionism it's just like a a branch
of public health right now like
let's talk about hostinism let's talk
about xena feminism let's talk about the
possibilities of
the human body um not just about
like transcending your body and like
going up into the cloud and that
enhancing our bodies in whatever way we
want on whether
that's changing our gender to enhancing
our gender to becoming more feminine um
and i'm
at the risk of um being uh someone who
has
unpopular views wouldn't want that right
um i think that
it's about so much more than like
being trans it's about
understanding the human condition
and reaching to higher metaphysical
depths
um perhaps you know you don't just want
to change your gender perhaps you
want to become um you know like a
queen or somebody who can fly
um that there are so many possibilities
when we talk about
transcendence and futurism here and i
definitely don't want to conflate them
with the uh immortality cult because
it's a
completely different world yeah when we
look into the future versus looking into
the past there's very different kinds of
possibilities there i mean
the post-human question um
and like what that does for us as human
beings
i think is like a pretty important one
in terms of um
contextualizing the human experience and
that's you know that goes beyond
you know masculinity or femininity at
all i mean that is like
that is kind of a biological quality
um yeah so definitely i i think you're
right to say that it is post-humanist
um thank you lisa for that provocation
really appreciated that i also love the
idea of the well
do i wanna invite anybody else to ask
questions um you know we're here we're
two brains
and we have things to say
i've got a question all right hi nice to
meet you guys
and thanks for the event um i was
wondering if you could expand a little
bit more on the commentary around
the great mother and specifically the
devouring aspect of the archetype being
i think more of like the energy of the
power i believe you guys said um
i think with my point of view i i see
the archetype
as a whole and that tonic element the
forgotten as
more of a repressive element of the
feminine something that needs to be
reclaimed and sort of
uh made uh sort of brought back
into the light and um a necessary sort
of darkness that that feminine element
brings um sort of balances out the light
element and kind of together they hold
to me like the core of the power and
you know just to throw it back a little
bit more to the comment about ursula
um i think like in her in her darkness
in her non-sexy hotness like she is
she's the baba yaga archetype she's the
devouring mother and she
through those dark initiations she
forces like the maiden to
to transcend to kind of go through
psychic transformation and
um the maiden kind of has her own power
in that case
her her openness her trust um
her naivety and it's kind of through the
bridging of these
uh moments that the feminine really kind
of takes shape and takes hold so
anyways just wondering if you could
expand just a little bit more upon your
ideas around that
oh yeah thank you for that comment i
think that was an excellent way of
talking about because i mean you're
bringing up an excellent point the
maiden has her own power
um i think that this is something that
uh is absolutely critical for women to
um address for themselves just on a
like day-to-day basis um
for a long time i denied personally like
the power
of my own kind of youth and vitality
as a young beautiful woman and it
uh is a kind of denial that i see
that's like weird it's like a weird kind
of self-deception
right it's like oh my god you can see
just like the
the worship of these beautiful maiden
figures this is everywhere it's like on
the internet it's like everything i mean
everything is this made in worship
um and yet you know individually women
i think don't necessarily kind of fully
understand
the implications of their power and of
course the internet like exaggerates
this specific kind of power
because it's so image oriented
which is also the realm you know that
the maiden walks in
with such such great asymmetrical power
especially over men um so i think that
you're totally right to call out the
the power of the maiden i think the
funny thing about it
um or i guess it's it's kind of a
uh unification of
the maiden and the kind of baba yaga or
you know the great mother archetype
and some sort of tension because of
course that's the other element of this
is that
you know women aren't some sort of like
monolith of of
perfectly aligned figures there's a lot
of conflict that happens between women
and there's often conflict uh between
and you can see this like that maybe the
story of snow white right so you have
the stepmother who is
cool and evil and ugly and you know
obsessed with her own appearance and you
have this beautiful
kind of uh this virgin character who
um she is jealous of so there's also
kind of these the tension
between these figures that um
creates creates these like dark
you know these kind of darker dynamics i
think for me
where where the great mother is such a
kind of yearning
is the fact that it has been repressed
and then that repression it has a kind
of allure to it
um it it draws me in on a personal level
and it also
and i i mean i think honestly what you
said is just so perfect because i would
consider myself to be in a maiden phase
right i'm like a young woman i'm not yet
mother i am not yet
crohn but it is the confrontation with
the virtual
of the great mother the idea of the
great mother that is forcing me
to kind of reconcile with my own
self-deception
with with the things that i don't wish
to see about myself that are dark
you know and the other thing that i
think about this is that
the acceptance of the great mother and
her kind of virtuality as a presence
that can come along with you um in my
eyes
is a gift because the devouring mother
is a real archetype i don't know
you know how everybody's relationships
with their mothers are but there is a
total presence of a mother
who smothers her children who
holds them close and does not let them
go even when they need to go
even when they need to be left even when
they need to be
cast away from the breast it's like get
out of here go and differentiate
yourself
and it's it's like totally um a pitfall
of the mother to hold her children close
and not let them become their own
and i see that as being kind of starting
to dance in this direction of the
devouring mother of embodying the
devouring mother
and so the process of coming
in contact with the great mother
archetype i'm seeing in myself
that which could become the devouring
mother
and to me that is like it's a gift to
get
a chance to work through those things
before i have children
so that that's kind of um
yeah my understanding of the matter and
i really appreciate your comment
thank you and if you want to respond go
ahead
i'm sure thank you that was a really
lovely response um i
i think you're hitting uh the nail on
the head there as well with where i'm
coming from which is that um all of
these confrontations are opportunities
sort of to
challenge like the current psychic
landscape and these
figures you know the devouring mother
the potential of that kind of
arises within us to show us our
potential
both shadow and light um so that we can
grapple with them and understand them
and integrate them as we prepare to move
into these
these sort of next stages and so
hopefully you know we we bump
into you know the great mother archetype
and she prepares us for the role of
motherhood and
at the same time also warns us of what
could be or what could go wrong or what
happens when we don't address
our darkness and how that can twist and
um kind of darken at the pool of of the
beautiful
kind of mother to child uh relationship
um
and yeah so thank you for the response
and
looking forward to more yay
i don't know who you are but i love you
i do too you you should come back and we
should
talk more
[Laughter]
yay another philosopher queen
oh yes um great we got some
excellent questions going in chat here
um let's see here and rachel do you want
to answer any of those provocations
while i kind of sort through the
questions
there's a lot of questions um what do
you think of us
it's hard to think i'm so
alexander this is going to think that i
actually have
not regret that i'm like
so um she might be a better person to
answer
that question but what i do understand
is that he
believes that there is a phallic nature
that
is being lost and i definitely see that
with a lot of what you would call the
the soy boys
um that is causing women to embrace
their more
masculine devouring nature and i think
that this is a positive thing
um like i know is there a single woman
um here who's once married um i've made
my mistakes right um
that it's very hard for me to meet men
who
um exhibit any masculinity at all um and
that has made me more in touch
with the dark feminine aspect of
myself um so yeah
i i definitely think we we are going
through a feminization
um in in this current zeitgeist and i i
believe that this has created a
a bunch of like hashtag instagram
pseudo feminists who are only willing to
discuss
the bright light and i do think that
it's very harmful
to the cycle of birth like uh listen you
were talking about
yeah definitely yeah i think this
question angen
is like uh i'll just read it out loud
just so everybody can
get it for the video um what do you
think of alexander bard's model of the
world being more feminine or more
phallic
uh his whole digital libido thing um so
you know i think i i i understand bard's
position which is basically there's no
phallus there's no phallus around
there's no authentic valleys basically
um what we're seeing is a kind of um
excess of femininity uh and you can even
see this in
um the kind of more excessive stages
of feminism where
you know little boys are being
encouraged to
you know take on feminine traits or to
dress up as
as girls you know like an actual kind of
um desire
and this i would say is the devouring
mother this is the devouring mother
showing up
in real life with with their children
um where she's like you know wants to
create the child and her
image of what is best for the child
and in a way is imposing a kind of
feminization on the child because there
has been a demonization of masculinity
and for bard right like the authentic
phallus
is um something that is very difficult
to attain
um it is a masculine pursuit and has
been traditionally
and um is something that's necessary for
the
perpetuation of civilization and you
know this is where his understanding of
religion
fits in um so religion is like a kind of
template or a process or you know a set
of kind of metaphysical precepts
that allows for a person to move
themselves
into a process of becoming the kind of
authentic
um phallic force of existence and um you
know the messiah
would be an example of a kind of
authentic
phallic figure and right now we have a
lack of leaders
in our in our world um there's a lot of
what
bard would say is like kind of peter pan
little boys running the show
who are more interested in their own
narcissism and their own need for
attention
than they are in actually doing the
difficult work of making hard decisions
and leading the world um and so well i
mean my question about this has been
what is
what is the kind of virtual phallus
right um so of course you know
men have penises that's like a pretty
direct
um relationship to the phallus uh but
the phallus as a
authentic phallus is not that which is
just inherently endowed
to a man it is not you have to work for
it you have to become
that thing and in that sense it's
virtual and
i wonder about can i do that
do i need a penis to have
the virtual authentic phallus i actually
think that there's a possibility that i
that i don't um i think that's a unique
kind of quality of becoming a
um integration of these two forces and i
think camille poglia i mean she
identifies
she identifies as trans and i actually
think that this is exactly what she
thinks of
is is this kind of virtuality of the
authentic phallus
i'm in her embodiment of this through
her the myriad kind of complexity of her
um sense of persona um and her way of
approaching and being in the world
is that which is the unif is the
androgen
is the unification is trans in a
transcendent
sense not merely that which moves
between
poles but is actually that which is
above the poles
in a kind of synthesis and a kind of
dialectic
um so yeah i mean this is one of the
questions that i've been working on
quite a lot in my own thinking is like
the bardian kind of um view of reality
and how that fits in with the polyand
view
and then where that kind of places men
and women in terms of
actualizing themselves and i'm really
hoping that we can have alexander bard
on to talk
through some of the elements that are
specifically around
um the feminine because you know he's
got
lots of things that he talks about but i
really want to nail him down on on this
specific element
so thanks for the question raven if i
could ask
quick clarification of course yeah um
i don't quite understand like how
society or the internet like such
large meta things can be
phallic or female in nature like could
you help us there
sure um so in order to get a handle on
that i think i'm going to reference
marshall mcluhan
um so marshall mcluhan for those of you
who don't know was a media theorist that
was
extraordinarily influential um in you
know the
50s and 60s and um he basically
outlines this uh
understanding of mediums right so his
classic statement is the medium is the
message
um so there's certain kinds of mediums
that have
a kind of grammar to them right so he
differentiates two there is the acoustic
medium the acoustic medium
is um perspectival
it's uh that which is
non-linear it kind of moves around you
it's receptive it comes
to you and i think that this maps on the
acoustic medium maps on
very well to the dionysian or the
feminine
the medium the visual medium
which is uh literacy it's writing so
acoustic orality that's the
communication medium
um and the literacy which is a visual
medium because you
you read the communication is sequential
it's delineated um it is
in this sense the apollonian which is
also associated with
the phallus right um so i think
grounding those ideas
in kind of properties that you can
actually interact with
um so reading a long book like one of
these
bad boys is is a like phallic endeavor
it is like an endeavor of the sequential
it is an endeavor
of moving um through a grammar that
pushes you forward through a linear
progression of time
to listen you know to to be around a
campfire to be in an oral tradition
um is not sequential in the same respect
and what mcluhan theorizes is that the
internet
is actually going to be a revival of the
acoustic
um that the qualities
of the acoustic medium will be the
qualities of
the digital medium and i think we've
seen this bore out so we're kind of
moving away
from communicating through long form
arguments this is something that you
know the enlightenment people are
freaking out about because they're
seeing this kind of
what they consider to be a regression um
but really what it is is a kind of uh
exploration of the medium of the
internet which is that which is mediated
through image
you can create images and you can uh
snapshot them so that they have their
own kind of grammar
and that is a new communication style
that has
dionysian elements um it's empathic it's
intentional
it isn't doesn't have to explicitly
reveal what it
means you look at a video and it
looks self-evident um what it means um
and yet it actually
is hiding i mean you can think about
instagram right
you you cultivate a kind of perception
but behind the camera you know your
house is in disarray right so there's
this like this distance between
um that which is presented and that
which is experienced
um and this medium
the digital medium has very kind of
feminine qualities in this sense so
um it i don't know if that helps at all
but i think um kind of grounding it in
some specificity
of medium is a really uh a good way of
accessing this and i would
absolutely recommend marshall mcluhan um
as a way to get a handle
on what it means to even say like the
internet is feminizing like yeah
i mean that i mean if you don't have the
context that sounds
patently absurd you're like what do you
mean by that um but when you kind of see
it as connected to these other
theoretical
um concepts it actually does open up the
possibility of understanding
how these elements are are connected to
one another
is there a mcluhan book in particular
you recommend
i will get back to you i'm thinking of a
lot of people
understanding media is his thick one
um the the medium is the massage is his
quick read
he does explain a lot of the
symbolic nature of dialogue
of just like generating messages on how
the media operates
on in an objective kind of systems
thinking approach
um so understanding media if you want to
like fully grasp
mcluhan and the medium is the massage if
you
just want the cliff notes um so yeah
he's definitely been a very
influential thinker in a lot of
philosophical circles
and i he he just explained this very
well um
in my opinion though i think that
he's um a little bit too
focused on empower um kind of like the
go
um in that way where everything seems to
be about like
transmitting power and like
gaining influence and i think a lot of
that like misses
out on the primal core
of the divine feminine nature not not to
get off into a tangent
um but that's my post the feminist
take um so
um yeah yeah i'm seeing some some good
links
in the chat um i actually i saw a good
comment from hannah um
just to take this in a
little bit of a new direction um i
thought the queen in snow white was so
beautiful um i felt the same way
and um even like maleficent played by
angelina jolie
you know maybe it wasn't like the best
dialogue that she had
um but the archetype that she embodied
was
incredible um even like mystique from
x-men i remember a scene where
mystique is trying to be more like the
humans
and then one of the yes my films and
magneto
is like you know that's beauty you know
like when mystique review
um she reveals like her true dark
essence
and i would definitely echo that and i
do think that a lot of the
dark feminine qualities have been
villainized in
hollywood and i think that maybe it's
it's time for for something new while
i'm reading about jessica jones here and
i love that show i think it's really on
the
same wavelength as what we're talking
about so um yeah
just some opinions okay
definitely so pretty
sure we only scheduled an hour here
so we're already five minutes up rachel
do you have any
closing statements philosopher queen
well i would just say that it's a
pleasure to be involved in this
and um i'm just seeing so many questions
what would a non-villainizer
here at the store this is actually what
we're creating
and yes we encourage everybody
to pursue this to tell your friends your
family about this panel and to
join us the next time um feel free to
recommend vlogs for queens to us and
yeah let's get this party started
yeah definitely um and you can uh if you
want to
suggest anything to us you can always
find us on twitter
um you know any questions or thoughts
you may have
and yeah we'll be we'll be back with i'm
i'm really hoping we can get nina power
on next time i'm currently taking her
batai course with justin murphy and it's
like
ah it's incredible um so
yes indeed well thank you all so very
much uh it has been
such a gift to have your presence here
um
and your consideration of our
wild thoughts and we will be continuing
this
i will do my duty as um
a host here and tell you all about a few
of the events that are coming up
uh so we have a really stacked lineup
here at the stoa
coming up so definitely take a look at
the full
um list but just to pick out some
specific things that i think
you definitely should not miss i've
really hearing some wonderful things
about
sand talk with tyson incaporta
who is an australian aboriginal man
who recently wrote a book called sand
talk and there's a lot of wisdom there
and we're really excited
that he could come to the stoa and talk
to us that's going to be on
august 18th at 8 30 pm eastern time
we have met a modern stoicism with
daniel schwachtenberger it's been
rescheduled so you can come and see us
um with daniel on august 24th at 7 30
p.m
eastern time and that's going to be a 75
minute
um event and what else we also have the
bioemotive framework live emotional
processing with
doug carteren and that's going to be
august 27th
at 2 15 p.m for half an hour so
lots of amazing things coming up here at
the stowe and then of course we always
have the wisdom gym
and yeah i think with that
oh and one more thing we have the scents
maker in residence as well which is like
a
series of three events um coming from a
different sense maker figure in
the kind of network that we all dwell in
this
month it is john robb talking about
networked tribalism
great um yeah and any other events
you can of course visit us at the stoma
dot ca
uh yeah so it's great to see you all
thank you so much
and see you next time thank you
bye see ya